A Guide to the Papers of Mark Twain, 1862-1946
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Letters
  - Mark Twain to Elizabeth Fairchild, Cambridge, MA, 1909 December 26; Card P, 1 p. (Box 6)
    Printed acknowledgement of sympathy expressed for Jean's death.] (w/env) (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain to _______, 1909 December 26; Card P, 1 p. (Box 6)
    Printed acknowledgement of sympathy expressed for Jean's death. Unused.] (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain, Bermuda, to Clara Clemens Gabrilowitsch, 1910 March 6; ALS, 4 p. (Box 6)
    Feeling fairly well after brief bronchitis; discusses financial matters; says she was right about Isabel V. Lyon and Lyon's faults; glad to know success of Miss Jones's book and is proud of Clara for championing her. Marcus] (w/env) (mourning stationery)
  - Albert Bigelow Paine, Stormfield, CT, to Frank Fuller, 1910 April 19; TLS, 1 p. (Box 6)
    Thanks from him and Mark Twain for kind note and food sent; says Twain very ill and Dr. Halsey and Dr. Quintard attending him.
  - Mark Twain to "Dear [Clara]", [1910 April 21]; AL, 1 p. (Box 6)
    Unfinished note; "You did not tell me, but I have found out that you -"
  - Albert Bigelow Paine to Frank Fuller, 1910 April 27; TLS, 1 p. (Box 6)
    Brief summary of Mark Twain's life and an estimate of his literary worth will appear in next Saturday's Harper's Weekly; article mentions Fuller.
  - Albert Bigelow Paine to Mary Mantz Moffett, 1910 June 23; ALS, 3 p. (Box 6)
    Inquires for Clara Clemens Gabrilowitsch if she ever received an important letter Clara wrote her; requests reply as soon as possible.] (w/env)
  - Clara Clemens Gabrilowitsch, Stormfield, CT, to Mary Mantz Moffett, New York, 1910 July 3; ALS, 3 p. (Box 6)
    Had not realized how ill little Anita was; will remain at Stormfield for the summer and leave for Berlin in October; hopes Anita will soon be better.] (w/mourning env) (mourning stationery)
  - Clara Clemens Gabrilowitsch, Stormfield, CT, to Mary Mantz Moffett, New York, 1910 July 8; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Enclosing check for $100 since she had sent only $500 rather than $600 previously; sorry her cousin has been ill.] (w/mourning env) (mourning stationery)
  - Clara Clemens Gabrilowitsch, Stormfield, CT, to Mary Mantz Moffett, New York, 1910 July 13; ALS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Sends receipt to be signed by Moffett for money sent previously; hopes she is much better.] (w/mourning env) (mourning stationery)
  - Clara Clemens Gabrilowitsch to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1910 September 23; ALS, 4 p. (Box 7)
    Thanks him for his condolences after her father's death; says she feels very much alone with no family; glad she has her husband.] (w/env) (mourning stationery)
  - Albert Bigelow Paine, New York, to Frank Fuller, 1912 April 8; TLS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Plans to see him again before returning to Redding; is writing day and night and under contract with Harper & Brothers; requests any information Fuller can give on Mark Twain and Twain's visits to him, Sam Small, and Twain's "Ohio sweetheart Pauline."
  - Charles Erskine Scott Wood to James MacIntosh Wood 1912 August 23, ALS, 3 p.
    Recounts in detail the printing of Date 1601; presents copy to his brother; recalls anecdote about Mark Twain's visit.
  - Willis Vickery, Cleveland, OH, to W. [K.] Bixby, New York, 1912 September 25; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Has not been able to get information re Mark Twain's letters to Mary Mason Fairbanks; mention he has heard how charming and intelligent she was; will send more information soon.
  - Edward Breck, [Boston] to [Harold] Bixby, 1912 November 30; ALS, 3 p. (Box 7)
    Asks on behalf of Albert Bigelow Paine if Bixby's father ( Horace Bixby ) would allow Paine to have copies of Mark Twain's letters for publication in Letters of Mark Twain; Paine will pay expenses incurred; would present Horace Bixby with some pieces of Twain's original manuscripts if he would like it.
  - Willis Vickery, Cleveland, OH, to W. [K.] Bixby, St. Louis, MO, 1912 December 4; TLS (copy), 1 p. (Box 7)
    Still unable to get information; gives details of Mary Mason Fairbanks ' life.
  - Willis Vickery, Cleveland, OH, to W. K. Bixby, St. Louis, MO, 1912 December 11; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Apologizes for getting his name wrong; encloses letter for him (TLS 1912 December 4 copy Willis Vickery to W. [K.] Bixby ).
  - Edward Breck, Boston, to W. K. Bixby, 1912 December 14; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Thanks him for permitting Albert Bigelow Paine to use any of his Mark Twain letters, except those to Mary Mason Fairbanks; cautions Bixby to confirm his legal ownership of the Fairbanks letters before publishing them for copyright purposes because the Mark Twain Company and Albert Bigelow Paine may own actual copyrights to letters. (Fairbanks pencilled in over Williamson in letter.)
  - Edward Breck, Boston, to W. K. Bixby, St. Louis, MO, 1912 December 18; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Discusses possibility that Albert Bigelow Paine as owner of Mark Twain copyrights may insist on printing Mary Mason Fairbanks letters; Paine would not object to Bixby printing a volume of letters but has not discussed matter with Paine; asks if he should say Bixby refuses to let Paine use the Fairbanks letters.
  - Edward Breck, Boston, to W. K. Bixby, St. Louis, MO, 1912 December 23; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Will send correspondence to Albert Bigelow Paine so that Paine may deal directly with Bixby; hopes they will find a solution.
  - Albert Bigelow Paine, Redding, CT, to W. K. Bixby. St. Louis, MO, 1912 December 26; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Has received correspondence from Edward Breck; recounts his understanding of the provenance of the Mary Mason Fairbanks letters and history of attempted publication; mentions law requiring permission of heirs and trustees to publish letters; feels Clara Clemens Gabrilowitsch, the trustees, and Harper & Brothers would prevent publication of a volume of Fairbanks letters.
  - Roswell Field, Morristown, NJ, to W. K. Bixby, 1913 January 4; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Has the Mary Mason Fairbanks letters; had thought Bixby could do as he felt with the letters legally; discusses his health, family news, and his house.
  - Stanchfield and Levy, New York, to W. K. Bixby, 1913 January 20; TL[S], 3 p. (Box 7)
    Informs him that the literary rights of the letters belongs to the Mark Twain Company and the trustees of the estate; heirs and trustees object to Bixby's publication plans; cites prior cases regarding literary rights and private correspondence; hopes he will not recall his consent to publication of his other Mark Twain letters.
  - Stanchfield and Levy, [New York] to W. K. Bixby, 1913 January 29; TLS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Sets forth history behind publishing volume of Mark Twain letters collected by Twain and Albert Bigelow Paine; hopes Bixby will provide copies of his letters to be included in book.
  - F. W. Lehmann, St. Louis, MO, to W. K. Bixby, St. Louis, MO, 1913 February 18; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Cover for letter for legal opinion sent to Bixby (TLS 1913 February 18 F. W. Lehmann, St. Louis, MO, to W. K. Bixby, St. Louis, MO).
  - F. W. Lehmann, St. Louis, MO, to W. K. Bixby, St. Louis, MO, 1913 February 18; TLS, 7 p. (Box 7)
    Legal opinion about manuscripts, authors' correspondence and copyright for materials Bixby owns.
  - F. W. Lehmann, St. Louis, MO, to W. K. Bixby, St. Louis, MO, 1913 February 19; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Cover letter for return of Stanchfield and Levy letter to Bixby.
  - Richard Burton, NY, to Dana S. Ayer, 1915 May 17; APCS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Regrets he has no autograph copies of Mark Twain or [James Whitcomb] Riley.
  - Albert Bigelow Paine, Bronxville, NY, to Dana S. Ayer, 1917 January 6; ANS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Expects to be in Bronxville in April and will talk over matters of mutual interest.
  - Arthur Burdett Frost, Madison, NY, to Dana S. Ayer, 1917 January 21; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Returning required proofs signed.
  - Albert Bigelow Paine, Bronxville, NY, to Dana S. Ayer, 1917 March 20; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Thanks him for informing him of Walter's death and will write his wife immediately.
  - Edward Windsor Kemble, Towners, NY, to Dana S. Ayer, 1917 May 3; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Says offer for [James Whitcomb] Riley book inadequate, especially for a book with full page original drawing by Kemble next to his dedication to Kemble.
  - F. J. Dowd, NY, to Dana S. Ayer, Worcester, MA, 1917 July 11; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Harper & Brothers does not have the Mark Twain photogravure plates; suggests he try photogravure printers Bliss used.
  - Franklin G. Whitmore, Hartford, CT, to Dana S. Ayer, Worcester, MA, 1917 October 19; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Is sending him a letter written by Mark Twain to him from Villa "Sittignano", Florence, Italy, in December 1892 as an addition to Ayer's collection.
  - John Mead Howells, New York, to Dana S. Ayer, Worcester, MA, 1920 June 19; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Asks $3000 for group of 97 letters of Mark Twain and William Dean Howells, most of which were published in a Mark Twain biography.
  - Mildred Howells, York Harbor, ME, to Dana S. Ayer, 1921 September 19; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Has discovered missing letters from collection Ayer bought; will send them to owner of collection.
  - Charles Erskine Scott Wood to Edwin Grabhorn 1927 July 13, ALS, 1 p.
    Sends his brother's copy of Date 1601 to him; recounts how got he got it from his brother. (on verso of ALS 1912 August 23 Charles Erskine Scott Wood to James MacIntosh Wood)
  - Charles Erskine Scott Wood to Edwin Grabhorn 1928 January 4, ALS, 1 p.
    Discusses TLS 1882 February 21 Mark Twain to Charles Erskine Scott Wood; mentions he returned the manuscript to Twain; speculates who "the charming Kentucky girl" may have been.
  - Lee Alexander Stone, Chicago, IL, to Mr. Peabody, 1929 February 25; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Cover letter for an ALS of Mark Twain's father he hopes will prove an addition to correspondent's collection.
  - Annie Moffett Webster, New York, to Mrs. Irvine, 1929 June 18; ALS, 6 p. (Box 7)
    Discusses Clemens and Moffet family genealogies in depth; says her Virginia relatives would know more than she does.
  - John Galsworthy to Cyril Clemens 1929 June 19, ALS, 2 p., with envelope.
    Gives him message for the Mark Twain Celebration; mentioning his enjoyment of Tom Sawyer and Huckleberry Finn.
  - John Galsworthy to Cyril Clemens, 1932 March 7; ALS, 1 p.
    Has made corrections in interview ( An Interview with John Galsworthy ); wants it printed as revised; thanks for sending pamphlet.] (tipped in Interview with John Galsworthy, Barrett PS 1343 .G3 1932)
  - Charles Erskine Scott Wood to Merle Johnson 1935 April 9, ALS, 2 p.
    Recounts printing of Date 1601; claims no authorized small paper edition; ordered type redistributed but did not oversee the redistribution; discusses printing of Date 1601 by Grabhorn Press; says Edwin Grabhorn was to sell the Academy copy and letters, but he is not sure if he did or not.
  - Ellen Shaffer, Dawson's Bookshop, Los Angeles, CA, to Frank Glenn, Kansas City, MO, 1942 September 28; TLS, 1 p.
    Is selling Morse collection as complete collection; it contains a copy of Adventures of Huckleberry Finn with a copy of suppressed plate tipped in; has not put separate valuation on item.] (laid in Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, Barrett PS 1305 .A1 1885a)
  - Arthur Swann, Parke-Benet Galleries, New York, to Frank Glenn, Kansas City, MO, 1942 November 11; TLS, 1 p.
    Discusses Glenn's Adventures of Huckleberry Finn prospectus with suppressed plate; mentions possible confusion for collectors and therefore suggests private sale of prospectus.] (laid in Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, Barrett PS1305.A1 1885a)
  - James L. Babb, Yale University, New Haven, CT, to David A. Randall, The Scribner's Book Store, New York, New York, 1943 February 11; TLS, 1 p.
    Discusses Yale's copy of the Adventure of Huckleberry Finn prospectus and compares it to Randall's copy.] (laid in Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, Barrett PS1305 .A1 1885a)
  - Frank Glenn, Melrose, MA, to Carroll Atwood Wilson, 1943 October 31; TLS, 1 p.
    Discussion of the Adventures of Huckleberry Finn prospectus and comparisons of different states.] (laid in Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, Barrett PS1305.A1 1885a)
  - George Hiram Brownell, The Twainian, Elkhorn, WI, to Carroll Atwood Wilson, 1946 March 31; TLS, 1 p.
    Recounts his interest in the excised illustration from Adventures of Huckleberry Finn; asks for information on plate.] (laid in Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, Barrett PS 1305. A1 1885a)
  - Harriet Sprague, New York, to Clifton Waller Barrett, 1950 November 1; ALS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Comments on Barrett's collections seen at Grolier Club; is sending him pictures Frank J. Sprague took at the wedding of Ossip Gabrilowitsch and Clara Clemens; says no photographer was present; encloses data on Whitman concordance (not present).
  - Samuel R. Morrill, Boston, MA, to Clifton Waller Barrett, New York, 1957 April 24; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Offers him Dana S. Ayer's collection of Mark Twain material and letters; gives brief history of Ayer collection.
  - Lucille McWane Watson to Mr and Mrs. Clifton Waller Barrett, 1964 October 13; ALS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Discusses the "Langhorne" part of Mark Twain's name with information about his father's friends, the three Langhorne brothers, William, Maurice and Henry.
  - Jared I. Edwards to Clifton Waller Barrett, 1971 September 27; TLS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Concerns death of Edith Colgate Salsbury who was a trustee of the Mark Twain Memorial.
  - Mark Twain to Unknown, n.y. [April 12-19]; AL, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Fragment. Postscript of letter; discusses assessments he has paid; Olivia unable to write but will send photographs later. No signature.
  - Mark Twain to Unknown, n.y. August 11; ALS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Mailed "Play acting" article; requests enclosed lines be added to article. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Unknown, n.y. August 18; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Thanks for the courtesy but there is nothing he wants to say publicly on these topics. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to [E. L. G.] Steele, n.y. Sept 18; ACS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Refuses invitation to a reading but hopes to come another time.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Mrs. [Sidney] Brooks, n.y. "the 28th"; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Says Olivia getting better and asks him to urge her to come next week; sorry her visit had to be cancelled but Olivia would hardly have been able to see her. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to Emma [Beach], n.y. Sunday evening; A card S, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Regrets he will be unable to see her because of business meeting at St. James Hotel; seems his business always fills his New York visits. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to Rudolf Lindau, n.y. Sunday; ALS, 3 p. (Box 7)
    Thanks him for his suggestions; draws many parallels with the story "The Philosopher's Pendulum" to his courtship of Olivia which he describes. S.L.C.
  - Will [Mantz], San Jose, CA, to Sam[uel E. Moffett], n.y. Monday; ALS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Re family business matters.
  - Mark Twain to Unknown, n.y. Wednesday; ALS, 1 p.
    Fragment. Has ordered two seats for his six lectures for correspondent but points out it will be the same lecture "word for word" six times. M.T.] (tipped in Mark Twain's Speeches, Barrett PS1322 .S5 1910)
  - Mark Twain to Clara Clemens, n.d.; ALS (facsimile), 1 p. (Box 7)
    Humorous notes and sketches.
  - Mark Twain, Grosvenor Hotel, NY, to Unknown, n.d.; ALS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Politely declines an invitation for an event in Boston. S.L.C.
  - Unknown to Grandson, ALS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Has had neuralgia and dental work; discusses reading books and scripture.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, n.d.; Calling cards, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Says he and wife will come but the girls are unable.] (w/env) (mourning stationery)
- Series III: Documents
  - John Marshall Clemens to Early Albertson, 1835 February 28; Receipt (Box 7)
    Receipt for balance due for town lots purchased from Clemens for the courthouse in Jamestown [Tennessee].
  - Typed copies of contracts between Mark Twain and Elisha Bliss and American Publishing Company: Innocents Abroad, 1868; Roughing It, 1870; Sketches, New and Old, 1870-1875;, with autograph annotations 1893 March 9 annulling 1875 February 12 agreement; Gilded Age, with Charles Dudley Warner, 1873; Tramp Abroad, 1878-1881; Diamond Fields, 1870; and Adventures of Tom Sawyer, 1872, 1868-1881; TD, 18 p. (Box 7)
  - Frank E. Bliss to Mark Twain, 1871 May 12; DS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Royalty check for $703.35.
  - Orion Clemens, Hartford, CT, to American Publishing Company, 1871 August 29; Receipt (Box 7)
    Copy of receipt for $308 from the American Publishing Company to be applied to Mark Twain's account; sheet torn from account book with partial copies of other receipts of American Publishing Company.
  - Mark Twain, Washington, DC, to J. M. Demerett, 1871 October 23; Receipt (Box 7)
    Receipt for lecture, "Reminiscences of Some Uncommonplace Characters I Have Chanced to Meet."
  - Elisha Bliss to Mark Twain, 1873 November 5; DS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Royalty check from the American Publishing Company with Mark Twain endorsement (S.L.C. signature).
  - Mark Twain to Frank E. Bliss, 1881 May 19; PDS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Transfer of 200 shares of stock from Mark Twain to Frank E. Bliss. With DS 1881 May 24 attached.
  - Power of Attorney of Mark Twain to Charles L. Webster, 1882 December 28; PDS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Grants power of attorney to Charles L. Webster to conduct Twain's business.
  - Contract between Mark Twain, Charles L. Webster, and Fred J. Hall, 1887 April 1; TDS, 7 p. (Box 7)
    Re: partnership in Charles L. Webster & Company. With A additions.
  - Frank E. Bliss to Mark Twain, 1891 October 8; TDS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Royalty check for $799.77.
  - 56 Receipts and copies for Prince and Pauper production (of Daniel Frohman ), 1891 October 12 -December 7; ADS (Box 7)
  - Bank notes, Charles L. Webster & Company to Jenkins & McGowan: 1894 January.25, 1894 February.23, 1894 March.21, 1895 April 2, 1894 January-1895 April; ADS, 4 p. (Box 7)
  - Agreement between Mark Twain and Frank Mayo for Mayo to dramatize the Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson, 1894 March 1; TDS, 3 p. (Box 7)
    With autograph additions and corrections; signed by S.L.C. and Frank Mayo.
  - 7 checks, 2 drafts of the Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company, 1894 March 3 -October 15; D (Box 7)
  - Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company: 2 carbons of Payroll March 6 signed Charles E. Davis; 1 typed memo March 5 about Bram Stoker stock account, 1894 March 5-6; TD, 3 p. (Box 7)
  - Power of attorney of Mark Twain to Henry H. Rogers, 1894 March 6; TDS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Grants power of attorney to Henry H. Rogers as administrator of Twain's and Olivia L. Clemens ' affairs while they are in Europe.
  - Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company stock certificate of Henry H. Rogers, 1894 March 9; DS (Box 7)
  - List of stockholders in Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company and their status; includes: Henry Irving, Bram Stoker, Orion Clemens, Mary Brushnahan, John Brushnahan, Dr. C. C. Rice; A Memo concerns Henry Irving's stock and Bram Stoker's installment paid to Mark Twain, 1894 May 7; AN, 2 p. (Box 7)
  - Agreement between Mark Twain and Olivia L. Clemens, 1894 March 9; TDS, 5 p. (Box 7)
    Agreement gives Olivia L. Clemens all Mark Twain's rights, title and interest in various type-setting machinery and Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company and copyrights of his published works. Signed for Twain by attorney Henry H. Rogers.
  - Consolidated Gas Company bill to Charles L. Webster & Company, 1894 April 7; DS (Box 7)
  - Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company stock certificate of Olivia L. Clemens, 1894 August 22; DS (Box 7)
  - Contract between Olivia L. Clemens and Frank Mayo, 1894 September 29; TD (copy), 1 p. (Box 7)
    Re dramatization of the Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson.
  - Bond of indemnity between Mark Twain, Olivia L. Clemens, and Bainbridge Colby, 1894 November 6; DS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Re debt owed to Colby.
  - List of shareholders in Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company, [ca. 1894]; T List, 1 p. (Box 7)
  - Contract between Olivia L. Clemens and Harper & Brothers to publish a uniform edition of Mark Twain's works., 1895 May 23; TDS, 5 p. (Box 7)
    Re publication of a uniform edition of Mark Twain's works with reference to copyright, plates, royalties, ownership of illustrations, and use of edition for school books.] (with ALS 1895 July 17 Charles J. Langdon, New York, to Henry H. Rogers )
  - Contract between Olivia L. Clemens and Harper & Brothers, 1895 May 23; TD, 8 p. (Box 7)
    Re uniform edition of Mark Twain works
  - Bainbridge Colby to Henry H. Rogers, 1895 July 18; Check (Box 7)
    Receipt signed on account of Olivia L. Clemens.
  - Subpoena to Olivia L. Clemens, 1895 July 19; PDS, 2 p. (Box 7)
    Subpoena to New York Supreme Court in case of Thomas Russell et al. versus Mark Twain re Charles L. Webster & Company.
  - Notice of dissolution of partnership of Charles E. Evans and Frank Mayo by latter's death, 1896 August 18; TDS, 1 p. (Box 7)
    Advertises sale of all assets of partnership, including script of the Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson by Mark Twain and Mayo, to be sold at auction September 1 1896.
  - Contract between Olivia L. Clemens, Mark Twain, and Charles Dudley Warner and the American Publishing Company, [1896 November]; TD, 8 p. (Box 7)
    Re sales and publishing of Mark Twain books.
  - Contracts between Olivia L. Clemens and Mark Twain and American Publishing Company and between American Publishing Company and Harper & Brothers and Olivia L. Clemens and Mark Twain, 1896 December 31; TDS (copy), 9 p. (Box 7)
    Re uniform edition to be published by Frank E. Bliss. With TLS December 15 1896 Frank E. Bliss to Henry H. Rogers re publishing of new book and uniform edition.
  - Contracts, 1896 December 31; TL, 27 p. (Box 7)
    5 copies of above contracts and letter.
  - Regius Manufacturing Company stock certificate of Olivia L. Clemens, 1897 April 19; DS (Box 7)
    With autograph memo pinned to certificate with information about Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company and Regius Manufacturing Company shares for Olivia L. Clemens, [Henry] Irving, and [C. C.] Rice.
  - F. Berkeley Smith to Frank E. Bliss, [ American Publishing Company], 1897 September 27; Receipt (Box 7)
    Receipt for Following the Equator cover design and three headpieces.
  - F. Berkeley Smith to Frank E. Bliss, [ American Publishing Company], 1897 October 13; Receipt (Box 7)
    Receipt for 5 tailpieces for Following the Equator.
  - P. Allan Gilbert to Frank E. Bliss, [ American Publishing Company], 1897 October 17; Receipt (Box 7)
    Receipt for 4 [unspecified] drawings.
  - Albert G. Reinhart to [Frank E. Bliss], American Publishing Company, 1897 October 19; Receipt (Box 7)
    Receipt for 3 unspecified drawings.
  - Frank E. Bliss to Olivia L. Clemens, 1897 December 4; Check (Box 7)
    Royalty check for $385.47
  - Supplementary agreement between Harper & Brothers, American Publishing Company and Olivia L. Clemens, 1898 November 11; TDS, 3 p. (Box 7)
    Re publication of How to Tell a Story and Other Essays, article on Austrian Parliament, and "In Memoriam."
  - Supplementary agreement between Harper & Brothers, American Publishing Company, and Olivia L. Clemens, 1898 November 11; TD (copy), 3 p. (Box 7)
    Copy of above.
  - Peter Newell to [Frank E. Bliss], American Publishing Company, 1898 November 15; Receipt (Box 7)
    Receipt for 6 drawings for Innocents Abroad.
  - William T. Smedley to [Frank E. Bliss,] American Publishing Company, 1898 December 13; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for one drawing for The Gilded Age.